All right. We are at
קה עמוד ב ka-heh amud bet at the bottom, המשנה. Hamishnah. Tell
me your name, I just
haven't met you
yet. My name is Yosef. Nice to meet you. I'm Hillel Rosen.
Rabbi Linden normally teaches this but he's on vacation. Yes, I was...
I was aware that
he usually does
and I was looking forward...
I was looking forward to that.
Awesome. Well, it'll be what it is. I'll be back...
back in Miami in a couple hours. Okay. בת ישראל מאורסת לכהן,
מעוברת מכהן, שומרת יבם לכהן, וכן בת כהן לישראל לא תאכל בתרומה.
Bat Yisrael me'ureset l'Kohen, me'uberet mi'Kohen, shomeret yavam l'Kohen, v'chen bat Kohen
l'Yisrael lo tochal bi'trumah.
So we're discussing the issues of who can eat תרומה trumah and
as you may have understood already from many of the discussions we've
had in the cases of תרומה, trumah, we say that a בת
ישראל bat Yisrael who has any connection to a כהן Kohen short
of... of marriage, or in the case of being
impregnated by a כהן Kohen but her husband is not in the
picture, he's either dead or well presumably that's what we're talking about,
and she has not yet given birth, or she's a שומרת יבם
shomeret yavam so the יבום yibbum hasn't yet taken place, she doesn't
eat תרומה. trumah. And the same is true of a בת כהן
לישראל, bat Kohen l'Yisrael, which is interesting because we would have thought
that with all of it... if the marriage is not sufficient to
feed the בת ישראל... bat Yisrael... תרומה, trumah, then you would think
that it would not be sufficient to take the בת כהן bat
Kohen out of the realm of תרומה, trumah, but apparently any kind
of connection to the... to the ישראל Yisrael on the part of
a בת כהן bat Kohen is... is good enough. Presumably because it's
a ספק, safek, right? So we hold
ספק דאורייתא לחומרא, safek d'orayta l'chumra,
and therefore if the בת ישראל bat Yisrael were not sure if
she's... if she's actually going to give birth safely, if the marriage
is actually going to go through or if the יבום yibbum is
going to go through, she doesn't eat תרומה. trumah. And on the
other side, if the בת ישראל... bat Yisrael... sorry, if the בת
כהן לישראל, bat Kohen l'Yisrael, right, is somehow connected to a ישראל,
Yisrael, maybe all those things will go through and therefore we'll find
out that really she shouldn't be eating תרומה. trumah. בת ישראל מאורסת
ללוי, מעוברת מלוי, שומרת יבם ללוי, וכן בת לוי לישראל לא תאכל
במעשר. Bat Yisrael me'ureset l'Levi, me'uberet mi'Levi, shomeret yavam l'Levi, v'chen bat
Levi l'Yisrael lo tochal b'ma'aser.
The same rules for תרומה trumah apparently go for מעשר ma'aser as
well. בת לוי מאורסת לכהן, מעוברת מכהן, שומרת יבם לכהן, וכן בת
כהן ללוי לא תאכל לא בתרומה ולא במעשר. Bat Levi me'ureset l'Kohen,
me'uberet mi'Kohen, shomeret yavam l'Kohen, v'chen bat Kohen l'Levi lo tochal lo
bi'trumah v'lo b'ma'aser. This is one of the odder
הלכות halachot we have. A בת כהן bat Kohen who is connected
somehow with a... with a לוי, Levi, or a בת לוי bat
Levi who is connected with a... with a כהן, Kohen, also eats
neither from תרומה trumah or from מעשר ma'aser on the off chance
that they're about to switch categories. Now what's interesting about this is
I can understand why a בת לוי bat Levi to a כהן
Kohen shouldn't eat תרומה. trumah. But why shouldn't a בת כהן bat
Kohen to a... to a לוי Levi eat... eat מעשר? ma'aser? As
we're going to point out later in the סוגיא, sugya, a כהן
Kohen is a kind of לוי. Levi.
So it's... it's a question, I'm not sure that the משנה Mishnah
is going to get into the answer. Charlie?
But the odd thing, she still... a כהן Kohen is part of
שבט לוי, shevet Levi, but anybody can eat מעשר. ma'aser.
Oh, so we're going to get into the question about who exactly
can eat מעשר. ma'aser. But that's exactly right. I mean that's... that's
an important point.
We're going to have to... as opposed to... I presume.
מעשר ראשון. ma'aser rishon. מעשר ראשון. ma'aser rishon.
We're going to have to... well, we're going to question that. Interesting.
I actually as... I guess I've seen the סוגיא, sugya, I assumed
that there's not even a question there.
No, I forgot it.
But let's see.
גמרא. Gemara.
So they say דתהוי זרה. d'tehavi zarah. So let a בת ישראל
bat Yisrael who gets married to a לוי Levi be considered to
be a זרה. zarah. זרה מי לא אכלה במעשר? Zarah mi lo
achla b'ma'aser?
Why shouldn't a זרה zarah eat מעשר? ma'aser? אמר רב נחמן אמר
שמואל הא מני רבי מאיר היא דאמר מעשר ראשון אסור לזרים. Amar
Rav Nachman amar Shmuel ha meni Rabbi Meir hi d'amar ma'aser rishon
asur l'zarim.
So this is the position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says
that מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon is אסור asur to זרים. zarim. And
how do they know this? דתניא תרומה לכהן ומעשר ראשון ללוי דברי
רבי מאיר רבי אלעזר בן עזריה מתירה לכהן. De'tanya trumah l'Kohen u'ma'aser
rishon l'Levi divrei Rabbi Meir Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah matira l'Kohen.
So we say
תרומה trumah
belongs to כהן Kohen and מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon belongs to the
לוי, Levi, this is the words of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah. By the way, the
תוספות Tosafot try to correct this to just a regular רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar because of the... it's just a strange thing to have
דברי רבי מאיר Divrei Rabbi Meir followed by רבי אלעזר בן עזריה,
Rabbi Elazar Ben Azariah, who's a senior to רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir?
I'm not sure if they're correct. In any case, permits a כהן
Kohen to eat to eat מעשר. Maaser.
So רש״י Rashi goes into the question of what exactly in this
statement suggests that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would not allow a זר
Zar to eat מעשר. Maaser. It just says כהנים Kohanim get תרומה,
Terumah, לויים Levi'im get מעשר. Maaser. It sounds like it's talking about
נתינה. netinah.
Well, that's kind of obvious. What's that? Well, that's kind of obvious.
Maybe. It could be that it's that it's obvious.
Although if we're talking about נתינה, netinah, we're going to say in
a moment, we're going to talk a little bit about the fact
that the question about can't a כהן Kohen eat מעשר, Maaser, whether
or not you can give מעשר Maaser to the כהן, Kohen, maybe
that's the חידוש? Chidush? I don't know. In any case, רש״י Rashi
tries to say that we have some kind of היקש hekesh here.
The fact that we compare תרומה Terumah and מעשר Maaser together, that's
what tells us that תרומה, Terumah, just as תרומה Terumah is not
to be eaten by זרים, zarim, so מעשר Maaser is also not
to be eaten by זרים. zarim. He also goes into the language
of רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar Ben Azariah who says מתירה.
matirah. The fact that he permits it, that suggests that we're talking
here about who's permitted to eat. These are the people who are
permitted to eat, presumably others are not.
So the גמרא Gemara says מתירה מכלל דאיכא מאן דאסר. matirah miklal
deika man d'asar. What
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar Ben Azariah says that we permit
a כהן Kohen to eat מעשר, Maaser, is there anybody who doesn't
hold that a כהן Kohen can eat מעשר? Maaser? Interesting parentheses, we're
going to see later on that in fact there is somebody who
says that, but in this case the גמרא Gemara takes this as
a grant as granted and then says אלא אימא נותנה. ela eima
notnah. Rather say that the that רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar
Ben Azariah says actually you can give מעשר Maaser both to the
לוי Levi and to the כהן. Kohen.
Sorry, נותנה אף לכהן, notnah af l'Kohen, right? You can give it
even to a כהן. Kohen. מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi
Meir? At this point we take the fact as granted. So what's
the reason for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that he doesn't think that
זרים zarim can eat מעשר? Maaser?
אמר רב אחא בריה דרבא משמיה דגמרא:
Amar Rav Acha b'rei
d'Rava mishmeih d'Gemara: כי את מעשר
בני ישראל אשר ירימו לה׳ תרומה. Ki et ma'asar B'nei Yisrael asher
yarimu l'Hashem Terumah. In the discussion of מעשר, Maaser, it talks, it
uses the language of תרומה: Terumah: את מעשר בני ישראל אשר ירימו
לה׳ תרומה. et ma'asar B'nei Yisrael asher yarimu l'Hashem Terumah.
So,
but it's interesting, it says I'm sorry, it says משמיה דגמרא. mishmeih
d'Gemara.
So right, I should actually say, make a point about that. רש״י
Rashi goes into this
question of משמיה דגמרא. mishmeih d'Gemara. So רש״י Rashi says רבו מפי
רבו רבו מפי רבו. rabo mipi rabo rabo mipi rabo.
What's that? אמר רבי אלעזר אמר זה אמר זה אמר זה אמר
זה, Amar Rabbi Elazar amar zeh amar zeh amar zeh amar zeh,
right? It's like a whole chain and here it's just like משמיה
דגמרא. mishmeih d'Gemara.
So right, I mean it is interesting that anytime that we have
these kinds of things where there's a statement משמיה דגמרא, mishmeih d'Gemara,
also sometimes we'll say אמרו משום amru mishum so and so, and
that's more of the תנאים Tannaim that we have that kind of
thing where you kind of you have this feeling of like we
always assume that something is a chain of transmission. So what is
it exactly that has to do with this משמיה דגמרא? mishmeih d'Gemara?
רש״י Rashi says,
so רש״י Rashi says it's to let you know that although we
don't have the entire chain, you should know that he's not making
this up.
Whenever it says משמיה mishmeih or משמו ד, mishmo de, it means
he didn't hear it directly.
In many, right, in many cases that's
true and that's not always...
אמר אמר.
amar
amar.
Right, yes. That's that's often the case.
In this case, I mean we could still have associated with a
name of some sort. It appears that he doesn't, except the that
we simply don't have the the transmission, the line of transmission,
and there they seem to be anxious to to say to you
that in fact that this is not coming, he's not making this
making this up, this is actually goes back to רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, this answer.
מה תרומה? Mah Terumah? Did you see something in the Artscroll that's...
well, רש״י Rashi kind of deduces that it's a tradition of רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Right, yes, exactly what he says. Yeah.
I just I heard you laughing so I thought that maybe there
was some point. Okay.
No, I didn't laugh. No, I'm sorry. I wasn't laughing.
So we
say מה תרומה אסורה לזרים אף מעשר ראשון אסור לזרים. Mah Terumah
asurah l'zarim af ma'aser rishon asur l'zarim. Right? Just as if since
since מעשר Maaser is called תרומה, Terumah, a kind of תרומה, Terumah,
so it has the rules of תרומה. Terumah. Just as מעשר Maaser
is a sort to... So this is תרומה Terumah is אסור לזרים,
asur l’zarim, so מעשר Maaser is also אסור לזרים. asur l’zarim. אם
התרומה im ha-Terumah חייבים עליו chayavim alav מיתה וחומש, mitah v’chomesh, אף
מעשר af Maaser חייבים עליו chayavim alav מיתה וחומש. mitah v’chomesh.
So the rules of תרומה Terumah is that a זר zar who
eats it gets מיתה בידי שמים, mitah b’yedei shamayim, and if he
has, and if he did it by accident, he has to give
it, pay it back to the כהן kohen with a penalty of
a fifth. So maybe מעשר Maaser follows the same rules as well.
אמר קרא, amar kra, we have a פסוק: pasuk: ומתו בו כי
חללוהו. u-metu bo ki chillalu-hu. You die for it because
you profaned it.
ויוסף חמישיתו עליו, v’yosef chamishito alav, and he should add also a
fifth to it. בו ולא במעשר. bo v’lo b’Maaser. Right, there’s this
language of ומתו בו, u-metu bo, that you will die for it,
for תרומה, Terumah, and not for other things.
עליו ולא על מעשר. alav v’lo al Maaser. Right? ויוסף חמישיתו עליו,
v’yosef chamishito alav, says the פסוק. pasuk. So we add, we add
a fifth to it but not to
מעשר. Maaser. לרבנן, l’rabanan, so in classical Talmudic style, the גמרא Gemara
asks: Okay, so now you’ve explained רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir so well
that I am now totally convinced that מעשר Maaser shouldn’t be eaten
by זרים. zarim. So what about Charlie, who says: Well, anybody can
eat מעשר, Maaser, what’s the problem? So what about the position of
the people who say you don’t eat, that זרים zarim can eat
מעשר? Maaser? So they say: מה תרומה טובלת אף מעשר ראשון נמי
טובל. mah Terumah tovelet af Maaser Rishon nami tovel. What does this
teach us? This teaches us that just as, not that זרים zarim
can eat תרומה, Terumah, but rather that, sorry, not that זרים zarim
are אסור asur to have מעשר, Maaser, but rather that just as
when תרומה Terumah gets mixed in with or when תרומה Terumah has
not yet been taken out of the כרי, kari, so that is
אסור asur with very strict penalties. So in the same way, מעשר
Maaser is also אסור asur in that way.
וכדתניא, u-kh’detanya, we have a ברייתא. braita. רבי יוסי אומר: Rabbi Yossi
omer: יכול לא יהא חייב אלא על טבל שלא הורם ממנו כל
עיקר, הורם ממנו תרומה גדולה ולא הורם ממנו מעשר ראשון, מעשר ראשון
ולא מעשר שני, ואפילו מעשר עני מנין? yakhol lo yehei chayav ela
al tevel she-lo huram mimeno kol ikar, huram mimeno Terumah Gedolah v’lo
huram mimeno Maaser Rishon, Maaser Rishon v’lo Maaser Sheni, v’afilu Maaser Ani
minayin? So
it’s possible that you wouldn’t get the penalty of מיתה בידי שמים
mitah b’yedei shamayim
if you just, that only counts for טבל tevel that has not
had any kind
of tithes taken out of it. But maybe if you’ve taken out
תרומה Terumah but you haven’t taken out the other tithes? Maybe you’ve
taken out מעשר, Maaser, maybe you’ve taken מעשר ראשון Maaser Rishon but
you haven’t yet taken out מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, and even מעשר
עני, Maaser Ani, how do we know that it’s still אסור, asur,
אסור asur with its with a strict penalty? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar:
לא תוכל לאכול בשעריך. lo tukhal le’ekhol bi-sh’arekha.
You cannot eat it in your gates in any way. ולהלן הוא
אומר: u-le-hallan hu omer: ואכלו בשעריך ושבעו, v’akhlu bi-sh’arekha v’sava’u,
and they ate in their gates and they were satisfied. מה שעריך
האמור להלן מעשר עני, אף שעריך האמור כאן מעשר עני. mah sh’arekha
ha-amur le-hallan Maaser Ani, af sh’arekha ha-amur kan Maaser Ani.
We go all the way down to מעשר עני Maaser Ani and
say just as when it says לא תוכל לאכול בשעריך, lo tukhal
le’ekhol bi-sh’arekha, you may not eat in your gates. What are the
gates? So later on we see that gates are an association with
מעשר עני, Maaser Ani, so here also gates are in association with
מעשר עני. Maaser Ani.
I hope that’s right.
Charlie? Okay, okay.
Great. ואמר רחמנא: v’amar
rachmana:
לא תוכל, lo tukhal,
and the Torah said you are not going to be able to
eat it. ואי מהתם, v’i me-hatam, הוי אמינא hava amina ללאו. l’lav.
And if we had heard,
I got confused on this one when I did this myself, hold
on a second.
If I had only, if I had if I had only heard
the פסוקים psukim that we just heard about
מעשר עני, Maaser Ani, right, what we said was that the initial
פסוקים, psukim, the פסוקים psukim that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir used, right,
those פסוקים psukim רבנן rabanan used to understand that מעשר Maaser is
טובל tovel the same way that תרומה Terumah is טובל. tovel. That
it’s אסור asur to eat when it’s not yet, when it hasn’t
yet been removed. So just as, so
then we brought this ברייתא braita from רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi and
that ברייתא braita also brings פסוקים. psukim. So it said if we
had only heard from those specific פסוקים, psukim, we would have thought
that okay, it’s אסור asur but only בלאו. b’lav. Therefore we need
to go back and hear from the פסוקים psukim of רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that it’s actually אפילו במיתה. afilu b’mitah. Yes, Charlie.
There’s an entire מסכת masechet dealing with what you do with produce
where you know that the תרומות terumot have been taken but you
aren’t sure whether the... Other tithes have been taken and it's the
entire premise in the מסכת masechta that it is only is that
it is only רבנן rabonun prohibited in most cases as מסכת דמאי
Masechet Demai and I can't... this could not possibly be consistent with
that because they're not going to let you biblically permit be permitted
to eat something that's ספק טבל safek tevel in such cases if
it's a...
so my understanding of דמאי Demai is that דמאי Demai are cases
where things have gotten mixed back in with חולין. chulin.
Whether or not it was... if it's a ספק safek of whether
תרומה truma has been taken or not taken...
It's not a ספק safek whether תרומה truma has been taken. It's
a ספק safek of whether
מעשר ראשון maaser rishon and מעשר... maaser...
מעשר ראשון maaser rishon or מעשר עני...
maaser ani...
it's a חומרא דרבנן chumra d'rabanan in terms of דמאי Demai to
take it even if maybe it was... it's not that it's אסור,
assur, it's that it's... it's just the requirement...
the דמאי Demai is a rabbinic requirement. Which is the reason why
you can take it בין השמשות bein hashmashot on ערב שבת. erev
Shabbat.
So I think that yes, I think that these ברייתות baraitot seem
to be in contrast with that position. Okay, that sounds true.
So we say אי מהתם הוה אמינא ללאו אבל מיתה לא. I
mehatam hava amina le'lav, aval mita lo. So maybe you would think
that it was only the לאו, lav, not the מיתה. mita. קמשמע
לן Kamashmalan from the פסוקים pesukim of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that
the rabbis learn that actually all of this kind of טבל tevel
is אסור assur even במיתה. bimita. לישנא אחרינא. Lishana achrina. We have
another version. לישנא אחרינא Lishana achrina I'll just point out is often
the case when you have one manuscript that says it one way
and another manuscript that says it another way, and then we'll eventually
create a situation where we put both... we just include the languages
of both manuscripts. This isn't a... לישנא אחרינא Lishana achrina is not
a Talmudic phrase to say, "Oh, we have another tradition." That would
be an איכא דאמרי ika d'amre or other... yeah, there are other
ways of saying that. לישנא אחרינא Lishana achrina is a scribal note.
And as they say, מעשר ראשון דטביל מדרבי יוסי. Maaser rishon detavil
miderabbi Yose. We know that מעשר ראשון maaser rishon becomes טבל tevel
from רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. מדרבי יוסי נפקא. Miderabbi Yose nafka. We
learn that from that case. אי מההיא הוה אמינא ללאו... I mehehi
hava amina le'lav... if that were the case, so... I'm sorry. We
ask a question, right? The rabbis learn from the פסוקים pesukim of
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that מעשר ראשון maaser rishon is
טובל. tovel. So we
say אי מההיא הוה אמינא ללאו. I mehehi hava amina le'lav. If
we'd only heard it from רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, we would have
thought for a לאו, lav, אבל מיתה לא. aval mita lo. קמשמע
לן. Kamashmalan. And therefore this is... that's what we learn, that we
learn מיתה. mita.
Rephrasing what we just said.
Correct. גמרא ואוקימתא כרבי מאיר. Gemara u'kyamta k'Rabbi Meir. How have you
solved the problem by saying that this is like רבי מאיר? Rabbi
Meir? אימא סיפא: Eima seifa: בת לוי המאורסת לכהן ובת כהן ללוי
לא תאכל לא בתרומה ולא במעשר. Bat Levi hame'oreset le'kohen, u'bat kohen
le'Levi, lo tochal lo biteruma v'lo bimaaser. So
at the end we say that a בת לוי bat Levi who
is engaged to a כהן kohen or a בת כהן bat kohen
who's engaged to a לוי Levi eats neither of these things. הכא
מאי זרות איכא? Hacha mai zarut ika? You haven't solved the problem
because we still have the attitude that a כהן kohen is considered
to be a זר zar by a לוי Levi and there's no...
why is that considered to be זרות? zarut? אמר רב ששת, Amar
Rav Sheshet, מאי אינה אוכלת דקתני? mai eina ochelet de'katani?
What does it mean when it talks about a... that a בת
כהן bat kohen doesn't eat מעשר? maaser?
We have a בת כהן bat kohen who is also a לוי,
Levi, so why should she be forbidden?
Right, that's very surprising. But didn't...
we're saying that although רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says תרומה truma is
אסור assur for the כהן kohen and מעשר ראשון maaser rishon for
the לוי, Levi, so nevertheless if she's engaged why should she be...
why should she be forbidden on her לוי Levi part? But that's
still, you know, like because you're in indeterminate status and you know...
yeah, but she's a בת לוי bat Levi in general even if
she were a בת כהן. bat kohen. So it's...
I mean
what you're pointing to is like is a conceptual... is a conceptual
difference between... I mean you can see two conceptual models we could
say here. We could say that either she's a בת לוי bat
Levi or she's a בת כהן, bat kohen, and therefore she should
be able to have the status of the least of those things.
Lowest common denominator. Or you could say like Michael says, that during
the time that she's in this period she's actually a בריה חדשה.
beriah chadasha. She's something else, neither בת לוי bat Levi nor בת
כהן. bat kohen.
So
the גמרא Gemara does not seem to consider that to be the
case. And frankly, it's a little odd to say that when a
בת לוי bat Levi is getting married to a כהן kohen or
a בת כהן bat kohen is getting married to a
לוי, Levi, she's now suddenly taken out of the status of both.
In other words, I can see that as
a... at the end of the day it's not the most intuitive
way of putting it.
Yeah, but you can also say that there's a גזירה gezeira *Gezeirah*
because it's just going to bring back to her she's if
she's going to be in her betrothed house and they're eating תרומה
truma. *Terumah* around there, we don't want
anyone she can have
the מעשר ma'aser, *Ma'aser* because she can be she's going to bring
the מעשר ma'aser *Ma'aser* to the כהן kohen *Kohen* or maybe the
כהן kohen, *Kohen* can't have מעשר ma'aser? *Ma'aser*. Hold on.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says תרומה truma לכהן la'kohen. מעשר ma'aser?
ללוי *Terumah le-Kohen Ma'aser le-Levi*. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* assumes
at that time, the גמרא *Gemara* says assumes when it says מכדי
איכא מן דאמר *Michdi ika man de'amar*, right? What? Doesn't it mean
we said about רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya *Rabbi
Elazar ben Azariah* who said מתירה לכהנים *Mattira le-Kohanim*, the גמרא *Gemara*
says מתירה לכהנים *Mattira le-Kohanim*? That's crazy. Nobody is אוסר *Oser* תרומה
truma *Terumah* to a כהן kohen. *Kohen*, מעשר ma'aser, *Ma'aser* to a
כהן kohen *Kohen*. Okay, but we're working now
and remember Ezra said the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* get everything
and לויים Levi'im, *Levi'im* get nothing.
Oh right, we're going
to get we'll get back to that. But רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir.
*Rabbi Meir* says that a כהן kohen. *Kohen* can eat מעשר ma'aser
*Ma'aser*.
So that seems to be the opinion of the גמרא *Gemara*. Now,
I mean I'm anticipating from you big questions that I'm not going
to be able to answer when we get to the end of
this עמוד *Amud*, because that question is going to seem to be
in doubt. But right now our assumption really is that כהנים kohanim
*Kohanim* can eat מעשר ma'aser *Ma'aser*. Why not? They are לויים Levi'im.
*Levi'im*. So רב
ששת *Rav Sheshet* comes along and instead of saying this kind of
indeterminate answer, which is certainly a possibility, he says that we simply
change the language or we change the understanding of what it means
when we say that she is that she's אינה
אוכלת ochelet *Eina ochelet*. What does it mean אינה אוכלת ochelet *Eina
ochelet*? אינה נותנת רשות לתרום *Eina notenet reshut litrom*. Right? If she
has a שליח *Shaliach*, she can't go she can't tell her שליח
*Shaliach* to go and he has
no right to her and get into her husband's stuff. Correct, right?
If she normally
we say that a person can send a שליח *Shaliach* to go
make and take תרומה Trumah *Terumah* for them, right? So a woman,
even a בת לוי bat Levi *Bat Levi* who could theoretically or
a בת כהן bat kohen *Bat Kohen*, sorry, who could theoretically be
giving the תרומה terumah *Terumah* to her father and so on, still
can't send a שליח *Shaliach* to go and take תרומה terumah *Terumah*
for her future husband. So we say מכדי נשואה נותנת רשות *Michdi
nesua notenet reshut*? So if she were married, would she have that
right? That's not one of the rights of a married woman. So
we say אין *In*, in fact it is.
והתניא *Ve-hatanya*: ואכלתם אתו בכל מקום bechol makom.
אתם וביתכם *Va'achaltem oto bechol makom atem uveitchem*. לימד על נשואה בת
ישראל bat Yisrael. שנותנת רשות לתרום *Limed al nesua bat Yisrael she-notenet
reshut litrom*. So
we have a מדרש midrash. *Midrash* that says that because it says
ואכלתם אתם וביתכם *Va'achaltem atem uveitchem*, that teaches us that ביתכם *Beitchem*
is like the wife, we often associate with the wife. So it's
saying that a married woman can give permission to go and take
תרומה terumah *Terumah*. אתה אומר רשות לתרום או אינו אלא לאכול *Ata
omer reshut litrom o eino ela le'echol*? Maybe it's saying that she's
allowed to eat תרומה terumah *Terumah* when she's married. אמרת *Amarta*, תרומה
terumah. חמורה אוכלת מעשר ma'aser הקל לא כל שכן *Terumah chamura ochelet
Ma'aser hakal lo kol sheken*? Right?
If she can eat the תרומה terumah. *Terumah* when she's married, right?
We say that married women can eat תרומה terumah. *Terumah*. Obviously she
can also eat מעשר maaser *Ma'aser*. אלא לימד על נשואה בת ישראל
bat Yisrael שנותנת רשות לתרום *Ela limed al nesua bat Yisrael she-notenet
reshut litrom*. And that's where we leave it. It teaches us therefore
that married women who are even ישראליות *Yisraeliyot* can give permission
to go and do תרומה terumah *Terumah*, go and take תרומה terumah
*Terumah*. מר בריה דרבינא *Mar brei de-Ravina* אמר *Amar*, לומר
שאין חולקין מעשר maaser בבית הגרנות *Lomar she-ein cholkin Ma'aser be-veit ha-granot*.
He has מר
בריה דרבינא *Mar brei de-Ravina* has a different solution from רב ששת
*Rav Sheshet*. רבנא *Ravana*? It's not I mean not clear to me
who it is. That's weird.
In any case,
it does say רבנא *Ravna*, רבנא *Ravana* or something like that. It's
not clear to me that it's a different person.
Yeah, they vocalize it רבנא *Ravana*.
Yep.
So he says לומר שאין חולקין מעשר maaser בבית הגרנות *Lomar she-ein
cholkin Ma'aser be-veit ha-granot*. That when that she herself cannot go and
collect the מעשר maaser *Ma'aser* from the actual
storehouses. Her husband has to go and do that, although she herself
is entitled we're also talking about the בת כהן bat kohen *Bat
Kohen* she herself is entitled to eat it.
Yeah,
she can't collect unless her husband's with her.
הניחא למאן דאמר משום יחוד *Hanicha leman de'amar mishum yichud* problem is
that she shouldn't go and do this because it's not appropriate for
her to be together with another a man beside her husband. אלא
למאן דאמר משום גרושה, gerusha, but if you think the problem is
maybe she'll be divorced and she'll go, people won't know that she's
divorced and she'll go and collect מעשר, maaser, and then you'll be
giving מעשר ma'aser to a זרה. zara. גרושה בת לוי מי לא
אכלה במעשר?
Gerusha bat
Levi mi lo achla bema'aser? So a בת לוי bat Levi, who
is a גרושה, gerusha right? Why shouldn't she eat מעשר? ma'aser Why
should that be a problem? So we say ומטעמיך גרושה בת כהן
מי לא אכלה בתרומה? Umitameicha gerusha bat kohen mi lo achla betruma?
According to your reasoning, then we also we should allow we should
allow female כהנים kohanim to also go and collect it because what
would be the problem of a גרושה gerusha? of a בת כהן
bat kohen who is a גרושה? She could also go and eat
תרומה.
terumah And that's the rule that she can go collect the tithes
if she's a בת כהן
bat kohen, for
her father.
Collect the תרומה terumah for her father.
Right. So but once she's married she's not allowed to?
So then the question is,
so we say אלא גזירה משום גרושה בת ישראל. Ela gezeira mishum
gerusha bat Yisrael. We simply don't want people to get into the
habit of giving to unaccompanied women because maybe sometimes it won't be
a בת כהן bat Kohen. or a בת לוי, Levi, it'll simply
be a בת כהן, kohen, sorry, it'll be a בת ישראל. bat
Yisrael אי הכי, I hachi,
many a חלל chalal still gets תרומה terumah. and מעשר? ma'aser Yes,
I think that's the case.
Otherwise we could be asking this question about everybody.
So we say אי הכי מאי איריא מאורסת? I hachi mai irya
me'ureset? If that's the case, if that's where we're going with this,
why are we talking about a woman who is engaged to be
married? אפילו נשואה נמי. Afilu nesua nami. Maybe somebody also who is
married should also be a problem. איידי דתנא רישא מאורסת תנא נמי
סיפא מאורסת. Aidi detana reisha me'ureset tana nami seifa me'ureset.
Since in the beginning where we were really talking about actual eating,
we were talking about being engaged, so in order to keep consistency
in the course of over the course of our משנה, Mishna, we
also use the language of engagement here even though actually we would
hold the exact same thing for a married woman.
Isn't the point that this גזירה gezeira only applies in the גורן?
goren? Like what's that about?
Well, the גורן goren is the moment when there's the transition from
the ישראל Yisrael to the whoever it is, the כהן kohen. or
the לוי, Levi. right? So at that's the moment when you have
to be concerned about who are you actually giving it over to.
You presume that once the person who's entitled to those tithes gets
it, that they're going to know how to deal with it. But
the ישראל Yisrael is the transition is a questionable transition, so you
really want to know that what you've got in front of you
is a לוי.
Levi So the there's two parties to this transaction. We're assuming that
the woman herself knows what she can eat and not eat, otherwise
it would be more than just the גורן. goren.
Yes, but the woman can eventually a woman might be a לוייה
Leviya for whatever a couple of years. I won't guess I won't
try to guess how many, right? She will be the wife of
a לוי Levi and be entitled to eat מעשר, ma'aser and then
one day they may get divorced, and then she's not entitled to
eat מעשר ma'aser? anymore. Now your assumption is that she's going to
know that she shouldn't eat מעשר ma'aser anymore, but she's used to
eating מעשר ma'aser and maybe doesn't bother her that much that she's
not allowed to, right?
Whereas the husband
himself is not there's not going to be a situation where he's
going to enter into the problem of not being a לוי Levi
at some point.
Not convincing.
Because of the I mean the problem with this גזירה is that
it penalizes it goes against the whole point in the first place,
like where is the woman who is still entitled to collect, where
is she supposed to get?
From her husband.
But she's divorced from her father.
Oh, so she has to get it from she gets it from
her father, she gets it from the well I mean it's not
particularly it's not particularly savory to say today in today's world, but
she her entitlement comes by way of whatever male לוי Levi, she
is now connected to.
But how can the husbands go to the granary, they're learning תורה
Torah all the time?
Okay, good question, we'll skip it for now.
But what I really don't understand though is how how do you
revise אוכלת to mean it doesn't mean that at all? So what
does the משנה Mishna say אוכלת then?
Oh, so I it doesn't sound to in this particular case it
doesn't sound to me like a חסורי מחסרא chasuri mechasra or something
like that where we're adding words into the into the משנה. Mishna.
It sounds to me like it is a an interpretation. She is
not she doesn't eat it. Where doesn't she eat it? She doesn't
eat it in the גרנות. granot. In other words she shouldn't collect
it by the from the גרנות. granot.
There they have it is it is difficult to understand the משנה
Mishna that way, but they have need because it's difficult a difficult
passage it's hard to understand the רישא reisha unless
you interpret the סיפא seifa that way.
That would be so weird way of saying it.
Yes, I mean often we have cases like that where the גמרא
sort of forced into Twisting its interpretation of the משנה Mishnah in
order to.
The ברייתא Beraisa says ואוכל קתני, v'ochel katani,
you know what I mean? Yes, sometimes it does say that, but
sometimes it doesn't.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. We have a ברייתא. Beraisa. תרומה לכהן ומעשר
ראשון ללוי. Trumah l'kohen u'maaser rishon l'Levi.
That sounds very similar to the to the ברייתא Beraisa of רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir תרומה goes to the כהן, kohen. מעשר ראשון maaser
rishon goes to לוי, Levi? דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה אומר Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya omer לכהן.
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya says that the מעשר
ma'aser, actually goes to the כהן. kohen, לכהן ולא ללוי, la'kohen v'lo
l'Levi, says the גמרא. How can you have it go to the
כהן kohen and not to the לוי? Levi The לוי Levi is
the one who's entitled to entitled to it. אימא אף לכהן. eima
af la'kohen. Say that what רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben
Azarya means is even to the כהן. kohen.
This is a recap of what we said before.
Wait, there you go.
So remember I said that there was different people.
It's not a recap.
It's not a recap because look at what the שיטה shita of
רבי Rabbi of רבי Rabbi of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva now. רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya says מעשר ma'aser goes אף
af to the כהן, kohen right?
Meaning that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say
that מעשר ma'aser. shouldn't go to the כהן.
kohen Right, and let's remember רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben
Azarya is a כהן. kohen.
Right, we're going to get that we're going to see that too.
Yes, that becomes that becomes an important piece.
Right, and the tradition of עזרא, Ezra, he's the tenth generation descendant
of עזרא. Ezra. Right, אלעזר בן עזריה. Elazar ben Azarya. Oh so
wait, you're saying the difference between what we said on up on
top?
On the top it sounds very
similar, right? רבי אלעזר בן עזריה מתירו לכהן, Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya
matiro l'kohen, right? It does sound similar but we translated that as
מתירו לכהן, matiro l'kohen, we say נתנו אף לכהן, notno af l'kohen,
that you can actually give it to a כהן, kohen. right? Meaning
that even רבי מאיר would agree that a כהן kohen. can eat
it, you just when you give the the מעשר ma'aser over, you
don't give it to the כהן. kohen In this ברייתא, Beraisa, we
have a question of who actually gets it, where רבי אלעזר בן
עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya would say that that
even a כהן kohen can eat it and it looks like רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say that a כהן kohen cannot eat it.
Right, and that makes much more sense. Because that would explain our
משנה. Mishnah. That's what our משנה Mishnah is saying. That's why, you
know, אוכל לבד ללוי. ochel l'bad l'Levi.
Yes, that's indeed.
That's what we hear up on top.
Yes, yes. We go.
I agree with you.
We say מאי טעמא דרבי עקיבא? mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Akiva? What is
the basis of רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? דכתיב ואל הלויים תדבר ואמרת
אליהם. dichsiv v'el ha'Levi'im tedaber v'amarta aleihem. בלויים קמשתעי קרא. ba'Levi'im ka'mishtayei
kra. When we talk about giving מעשר, ma'aser, we're talking about לויים,
Levi'im. we're not talking about anybody else.
ואידך כרבי יהושע בן לוי. v'idach k'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. The other
side, רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya. says this is
the שיטה shita of רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי בעשרים וארבעה מקומות נקראו כהנים לויים. d'amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi b'esrim v'arba'ah mekomos nikra'u kohanim Levi'im. In twenty-four
places, כהנים kohanim are called לויים. Levi'im. וזה אחד מהם. v'zeh echad
mehem. This is one of the places where it says ואמרת אליהם
בלוי sorry ואל
הלויים תדבר. This is one of the places where
כהנים kohanim are called לויים. Levi'im. And if you look up this
פסוק, pasuk, it does it appears he's actually right, רבי יהושע בן
לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. That
it says ואל הכהנים הלויים v'el hakohanim ha'Levi'im and so on. So
it appears to be that that in this case, this is a
case where כהנים kohanim are called לויים. Levi'im רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
it's interesting, a little contrary to his to his דרך, derech, is
well, in accordance with his דרך, derech, is reading that פסוק pasuk
very narrowly, which allows him to make a מדרש. Yes, Charlie?
We're using יחזקאל Yechezkel as the source for what כהנים kohanim do?
Yes. And didn't יחזקאל Yechezkel contradict an awful lot... yeah, he was
כהן. kohen. He was כהן. Kohen Yes, יחזקאל Yechezkel was a כהן.
Kohen But a lot of his a lot of the הלכות halachos
that he brings down flatly contradict things in the...
So yes, but the תלמוד Talmud still treats יחזקאל Yechezkel as a
source to tell us how כהנים kohanim and how the מקדש Mikdash
ought to be and then they often end up in the תלמוד
Talmud often ends up in questions about oh, well what do we
do with the fact that we have a a פסוק pasuk over
here that says this and a פסוק pasuk over יחזקאל Yechezkel that
says something else and tries to make some kind of synthesis.
There was an effort to exclude יחזקאל Yechezkel from תנך. Tanakh.
Yeah, we've seen it.
Yeah, we've seen it, yeah.
But רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi follows he's generations
after רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya רבי אלעזר בן
עזריה
Rabbi Elazar
ben
Azarya is we're saying that רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi is stating something which was what רבי אלעזר
בן
עזריה's
Rabbi Elazar
ben Azarya. thoughts were. Yes,
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi didn't know that he
was giving the answer to a question of רבי אלעזר בן עזריה.
Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
had a simple
מדרשי midrashic point. His point is to say oh, how interesting, the
כהנים kohanim in twenty-four places are called לויים. Levi'im And this is
one of them. והכהנים הלויים בני צדוק. v'hakohanim ha'Levi'im bnei Tzadok. So
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says ורבי עקיבא הכא לא מצית אמרת.
v'Rabbi
Akiva hacha lo matzit amrat.
In our case, the case that I'm citing, you can't say that
one of them. Right? This is not one of them, דכתיב אכלתם
אתו בכל מקום, dechtiv achaltem oto bechol makom, because it says you
should eat the מעשר ma'aser. בכל מקום. bechol makom מי שיכול לאכלו
בכל מקום, Mi sheyachol le'ochlo bechol makom, somebody who can actually eat
the מעשר ma'aser. in any place. יצא כהן שאין יכול לאכלו בבית
הקברות. Yatza kohen she'ein yachol le'ochlo bebeit hakvarot. A כהן Kohen is
not going to count, he can't eat it any place because a
כהן Kohen can't go into a cemetery.
He suggested eating stuff like that in a cemetery.
Yeah, take a picnic lunch. ואידך, Ve'idach, so the other side of
אלעזר בן עזריה Elazar ben Azaryah says to him, כל היכא דבעי,
kol heicha deba'ei, right, you can eat it wherever you want, not
you have to be able to eat it every place. דלא בעי
חומה, Delo ba'ei chomah, that you don't need to eat it inside
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ואכלה בטומאת הגוף ללקי. Ve'achlei betumat haguf lalkei.
And also you can eat it in when you're טמא. tamei. So
these things make a difference, so
the כהן Kohen still can be allowed to. It's not that בכל
מקום means that you have to indeed be able to eat it
in every single place. האי גינתא, Hai ginta, there was a garden
דהוה שקיל dehavah shaki רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah
מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon מינה. mina. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar
ben Azaryah
would collect the מעשר ma'aser from this place. So just like we
heard that רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah was a
כהן. Kohen אזל רבי עקיבא אהדריה לפתחא דבי קברי. Azal Rabbi Akiva
ahadrei lapitcha devei kevirei.
And he brought רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah by
the arm and walked him to the entrance of the cemetery to
say as though to say, you know, okay, you think you can
eat this, go ahead go in and eat it. אמר עקיבא בתמילו
ואנא חיי. Amar Akiva betamilo va'ana chayei.
He said Akiva with his pack, a תמילו tamilo the
רש״י Rashi tells us is like a leather pouch where a shepherd
keeps his food. So you עקיבא, Akiva, you were a shepherd, you
have your lunchbox, but me, I live the good life.
Frankly, I'm not entirely sure
what he's saying. I looked at a few of the translations to
try to understand.
No, is he saying where
am I supposed to get food from?
Ah, okay, that's good.
Because רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah was wealthy
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was not from a wealthy background. He
was a wealthy man.
But
this is when
he speaks as a I didn't see that.
Yeah,
but when רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah is saying
it, he's saying it not for himself, he's saying it for כהנים
kohanim in general. Where are we כהנים kohanim supposed to.
Very good, very good, יפה מאוד. yafeh me'od.
איתמר, Itmar, we have a statement in the בית מדרש beit midrash
of the אמוראים. amoraim. מפני מה קנסו לויים במעשר? Mifnei mah kinsu
levi'im bema'aser?
Why was it that the לויים Levi'im? were punished and the מעשר
ma'aser. was taken away from them?
Well, there's I think there are a lot of layers in this
עקיבא בתמילו. Akiva betamilo. Yeah, go ahead. As you said I think
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה was wealthy, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was more
poor background, was a shepherd.
Right, it's
that he's dismissing him at the same time that he's also saying
that, that's right, that's right. So מפני מה קנסו
לויים במעשר? mifnei mah
kinsu levi'im bema'aser?
Why is it that the לויים Levi'im lost the, were not permitted
to take the מעשר? ma'aser, פליגי בה רבי יונתן וסביא. Pligi ba
Rabbi Yonatan vesavya.
רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan argued with the elders. חד אמר שלא עלו
בימי עזרא. Chad amar shelo alu bimei Ezra. One said it's a
punishment to the fact that they didn't come to ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael in the time of עזרא. Ezra. וחד אמר כדי שיסמכו כהנים
עליו בימי טומאתן. Vechad amar kedei sheyismchu kohanim alav bimei tumatan. And
one said it was in order for the כהנים kohanim to rely
on it when they got, when they were טמאים. teme'im. בשלמא למאן
דאמר שלא עלו, Bishlama leman de'amar shelo alu,
maybe according to the per, okay, I understand according to the person
who said because they didn't make עליה. aliyah. משום הכי קנסו. Mishum
hachi kinsu.
That's the way, that's the reason that they punished them. Okay, you
don't want to come to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, fine, you don't
get
the benefit of living in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. אלא למאן דאמר
כדי שיסמכו עליו כהנים בימי טומאתן, Ella leman de'amar kedei sheyismchu alav
kohanim bimei tumatan, משום כהנים קנסו לויים? mishum kohanim kinsu lelevi'im? What,
in the only way, the only way you can give כהנים kohanim
what to eat is to take something away from the לויים? Levi'im?
That's because the כהנים Kohanim. are hungry when they're טמאים, teme'im, why
should the לויים Levi'im, have that, why should that be the problem
of the לויים?
Levi'im, He had a bad day last week.
אלא כולי עלמא קנסא, Ella kulei alma kensa, קנסא שלא עלו בימי
עזרא. kensa shelo alu bimei Ezra.
Everybody agrees that it's actually the punishment is because they didn't make
עליה aliyah in the time of עזרא. Ezra. והכא בהכא מיפלגי, Ve'hacha
behacha miflagi, and this is what they're arguing about. מר סבר קנסא
לעניים ומר סבר לכהנים. Mar savar kensa le'ani'im umar savar lekohanim. One
guy thinks that, okay, the מעשר ma'aser. no longer belongs to the
לויים, Levi'im, now it should be צדקה, tzedakah, should just go to
the poor people. And the other one says, no, if we're going
to do anything with it.
I can imagine
כהנים Kohanim as מעשר עני. ma'aser ani. Right, no, this is מעשר
ראשון ma'aser rishon that we're talking about. But okay, so if we're
not giving it to... One guy thinks that okay the מעשר no
longer belongs to the לויים, Levi'im, now it should be צדקה, tzedakah,
should just go to the poor people. And the other one says,
no, if we're going to do anything... wait, we didn't mention years
as מעשר עני. ma'aser ani. Right, no, this is מעשר ראשון ma'aser
rishon that we're talking about. But okay, so if we're not giving
it to the לויים, Levi'im. we should give it to the poor.
So the other guy says, okay, but this is still מעשר, who
should it go to? Should go to the כהנים. Kohanim, מי אמר
סבר כהנים בימי טומאתם עניים נינהו Mi amar savar Kohanim bimei tum'atam
ani'im ninhu
because when כהנים Kohanim become טמאים, teme'im, suddenly they have nothing to
eat. And so they really, those are the, those are the real
עניים. ani'im.
They could eat חולין, chullin, but they don't have access to חולין
chullin in the way that עניים ani'im have.
They don't have fields.
Right, they don't have any access.
So this is a good way to get them what they need.
בשלמא למאן דאמר קנסו לעניים משום הכי אהדרי רב עקיבא לפתחא דבי
קברי אלא למאן דאמר לכהנים אמאי אהדרי לפתחא דבי קברי. Bishlama leman
de'amar kansu la'ani'im mishum hachi ahadrei Rabbi Akiva lepitcha devei kivrei ela
leman de'amar laKohanim amai ahadrei lepitcha devei kivrei.
So the reason we brought this whole thing
in is to bring a question on Rabbi Akiva. We say, okay,
for the person who said that the מעשר from now on should
go to the עניים, ani'im, so okay, I understand why Rabbi Akiva
was brought, was sarcastic or something, brought Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah to
the entrance of the cemetery to show him that he's not entitled
to eat מעשר. Just one more second.
But according to the one who says that מעשר should go to
the כהנים, Kohanim? what justification does Rabbi Akiva have?
So I think maybe it means that Rabbi Akiva blocked the access
to the storage by making it a by establishing it as a
בית קברות beit kvarot something because that would fit better here אהדרי
לפתחא דבי קברי.
ahadrei lepitcha devei kivrei. He blocked out all the כהנים Kohanim from...
Oh. Everybody's...
it's the only entrance.
Fantastic,
I assumed the אהדרי ahadrei was אהדרי רב אלעזר
בן
עזריה
ahadrei Rabbi Elazar ben
Azariah
but this subject, if
the entrance is through the cemetery, the כהן Kohen can never get
there or if he's there he's stuck and can never leave.
Right, that's how this makes sense because like why would why does
Rabbi Akiva block all כהנים?
Kohanim Fantastic, thank you, I'm sorry for messing that up.
Okay, so we still have the
question: why does Rab- so
why does Rabbi Akiva do this? Why does he prevent Rabbi Elazar
ben Azariah from doing this?
Making his collection?
Right. הכי קאמר ליה, Hachi ka'amar leh, this is what he said
then. אי דאתית בתורת קנס אית לך. Ei de'atit betorat knas it
lach. If you're coming to take it as a as a קנס,
knas, then as you know as a punishment to the לויים, Levi'im.
okay, as long as you understand. ואי דאתית בתורת חלוקה לית לך.
Ve'ei de'atit betorat chalukah leit lach. As long as you understand that
this is not your legal ten- this is not your legal food.
Right, you're taking it because there was a קנס, knas, as long
as you understand that you're entitled, but if you think that you're
taking it in according to some other some other way according to
the basic law, then that's not acceptable. Yes.
If I have a field and I'm taking תרומה and I'm taking
מעשר, I can give the תרומה to any כהן Kohen I want.
The כהן Kohen doesn't have the right to come into my field
and take the תרומה without it.
Yes, that's correct.
So how is it that Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah was within a
garden that probably wasn't even his?
No, presumably he was taking it from the owner of the garden.
How- how did he know what was מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon either?
Right, he would go there, he would collect תרומה and...
Right, right, but the owner has to separate the stuff.
Correct. So the owner has taken that stuff out and he then
gives the you know each part to different people as he chooses
and Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah was collecting the מעשר. I don't think
anybody thinks that he was walking in and just you know eating
tomatoes off the tomato plant.
But there's a difference with פאה pe'ah and לקט ושכחה, leket veshichcha,
the poor person can come in against the wishes of the owner.
Yes, so but that is not the case for a כהן or
לוי Levi. despite the fact that now we have said that כהנים
בימי טומאתם עניים נינהו, Kohanim bimei tum'atam ani'im ninhu, we I don't
think that we would apply that.
Okay, that was where I was getting at.
I didn't- no, it doesn't appear to be the case.
ומנלן
דלא סליקו בימי עזרא?
Umanlan delo
saliku bimei Ezra?
So now we just have a a simple question on the תנ"ך.
Tanach. How do we know that they didn't make עליה aliyah in
the time of עזרא? Ezra? So we say דכתיב ואקבצם אל הנהר
הבא אל אהוא ונחנה שם ימים שלשה ואבינה בעם ובכהנים ומבני לוי
לא
מצאתי שם. Dechtiv va'akbetzem el hanahar haba el Ahava venachaneh sham yamim
sheloshah va'avinah ba'am uvakohanim umibnei Levi lo matzati sham.
So when when עזרא Ezra was taking the people there is a
פסוק מפורש pasuk meforash that says that he looked around, he couldn't
find any לויים. Levi'im אמר רב חסדא בתחילה לא היו מעמידים שוטרים
אלא מן הלוים. Amar Rav Chisda batchilah lo hayu ma'amidim shotrim ela
min haLevi'im. Initially
they wouldn't make שוטרים, shotrim, scribes or people of officials, they
would only take officials from the לויים. שנאמר ושוטרים הלוים לפניכם. Shene'emar
veshotrim haLevi'im lifneichem. And then
we have a פסוק pasuk that tells us that the לויים have
to be the שוטרים. shotrim. עכשיו אין מעמידים שוטרים אלא מישראל. Achshav
ein ma'amidim shotrim ela miYisrael.
But now we only take. officials from ישראל Yisrael שנאמר והשוטרים הרבים
בראשיכם. she-ne-emar ve-shoterim ha-rabim be-rasheichem.
So now we always take the שוטרים shoterim from ישראל Yisrael because
and he quotes something that says והשוטרים הרבים בראשיכם, ve-ha-shoterim ha-rabim be-rasheichem,
the officials will be at their head. מסורת הש"ס Masoret ha-Shas says
פסוק זה לא נמצא בתנ"ך. pasuk ze lo nimtza ba-Tanach. He says
this is not a פסוק, pasuk, I don't know where they're taking
this from.
So very interesting, I'm not, you know, he apparently has either, you
know, has some פסוק pasuk in his head that he's trying to
refer to, it doesn't appear that
the מפורשים meforshim had to address this.
Oh yeah, what do they have to say?
They say that it's most likely a פסוק pasuk in דברים Devarim
א' aleph פסוק י"ג. pasuk yud-gimmel. הבו לכם אנשים חכמים ונבונים וידועים
לשבטיכם ואשימם בראשיכם.
havu lachem anashim
chachamim u-nevonim vi-yedu'im le-shivteichem va-ashimem be-rasheichem.
Is
that referring to that, it's just not quoting properly.
Perhaps it's quoting really badly. Very badly.
I mean, the מפורשים בתורה,
meforshim ba-Torah, you know, you wouldn't think they'd get that.
Oh they do.
I mean, first of all we also know that חז"ל Chazal occasionally
have a different נוסח nusach of the
מקרא.
Mikra. If it's changed from וידועים vi-yedu'im to לשבטיכם, le-shivteichem, if they're
known there they must be הרבים? ha-rabim? But it's weak. It's really
is a פסוק pasuk in דברים.
Devarim. Yeah.
It's challenging.
Okay,
on to the next משנה. mishnah. מתניתין. Matnitin. בת ישראל שניסת לכהן
תאכל בתרומה. bat Yisrael she-nisset le-Kohen tochal bi-terumah. מת ולא הימנו בן
תאכל בתרומה.
met ve-la himenu ben
tochal bi-terumah. ניסת ללוי תאכל במעשר. nisset le-Levi tochal be-ma'aser. מת ולא
הימנו בן תאכל במעשר. met ve-la himenu ben tochal be-ma'aser. ניסת לישראל
לא תאכל לא בתרומה ולא במעשר.
nisset le-Yisrael lo tochal lo
bi-terumah ve-lo be-ma'aser. מת ולא הימנו בן לא תאכל לא בתרומה ולא
במעשר. met ve-la himenu ben lo tochal lo bi-terumah ve-lo be-ma'aser. So
a בת ישראל Yisrael, can go through the entire gamut if she
and she's at her best I guess when she has a son
who is a כהן and a son who is a לוי. Levi,
A בת ישראל Yisrael who marries a כהן can eat תרומה. And
if her husband dies, if she has a כהן son, then she
can continue to eat תרומה. If she then gets remarried to a
לוי, Levi, then she can eat מעשר. And if he dies and
she has a...
but she can't eat תרומה.
Right, I guess the תרומה is gone... I was thinking about a
בת כהן. So right, if she has a son who is a
לוי, Levi then she can still eat מעשר but the תרומה is
gone from her. ניסת לישראל לא תאכל לא בתרומה ולא במעשר. nisset
le-Yisrael lo tochal lo bi-terumah ve-lo be-ma'aser. When she gets remarried to
a ישראל, Yisrael then she can no longer eat either of these
things. And if he dies and she still
has a son by him, then she can't eat either תרומה or
מעשר. מת בנה מישראל. met benah mi-Yisrael. So now we can go
backwards. If her son
ישראל who
was making her not eat,
right, who was preventing her from having access to מעשר, if he
dies, תאכל במעשר. tochal be-ma'aser. מת בנה מן הלוי תאכל בתרומה. met
benah min ha-Levi tochal bi-terumah. מת בנה מן הכהן מן הכהן לא
תאכל לא בתרומה ולא במעשר. met benah min ha-Kohen min ha-Kohen lo
tochal lo bi-terumah ve-lo be-ma'aser. Yes.
Is there a is this just a minor child or is this
lifelong?
Yes, it's lifelong. Any child. As long as she has living offspring
who are of the tribe that she married into. Yes, that's right.
I thought you were saying even if a minor then it still
works.
And the answer is yes, right.
Certainly works for the
opposite. Yes, that's correct. בת כהן שניסת
לישראל
לא תאכל.
bat Kohen she-nisset
le-Yisrael lo tochal.
Now we're going to go in the opposite direction now. בת כהן
שניסת לישראל לא תאכל בתרומה. bat Kohen she-nisset le-Yisrael lo tochal bi-terumah.
מת ולא הימנו בן לא תאכל בתרומה. met ve-la himenu ben lo
tochal bi-terumah. ניסת ללוי תאכל במעשר. nisset le-Levi tochal be-ma'aser. מת ולא
הימנו בן תאכל במעשר. met ve-la himenu ben tochal be-ma'aser. ניסת לכהן
תאכל בתרומה. nisset le-Kohen tochal bi-terumah. מת ולא הימנו בן תאכל בתרומה.
met ve-la himenu ben tochal bi-terumah. So this is very interesting, although
apparently she has a בן ישראל, ben Yisrael, she is still entitled
to eat תרומה by way of her בן כהן. ben Kohen. מת
בנה מן הכהן לא תאכל. met benah min ha-Kohen lo tochal. I
think so, I think that's what it sounds like. She married the
כהן last, that was her last.
That's right and that's what apparently makes the difference.
That's an upgrade. Yeah.
מת בנה מן הכהן לא תאכל בתרומה.
met benah min ha-Kohen
lo tochal bi-terumah. מת בנה מן הלוי לא
תאכל במעשר.
met benah min ha-Levi
lo tochal be-ma'aser. מת בנה מישראל חוזרת לבית אביה.
met
benah
mi-Yisrael chozeret le-veit avi-ha.
So
as
right, after her sons die unfortunately, she again and again
right goes
back to her old status. So if
her כהן son dies, then she can no longer eat תרומה. If
her לוי son dies, she can no longer eat מעשר. If her
ישראל son dies, then she goes back to her original status. Like
her, like her in her youth she can eat the bread of
her father. And we do find in some, yes, בית אביה Beit
Aviha is figured like what if her father has died? Yes, בית
אב Beit Av is a general term that we have for her,
yeah her, right, think about לך לך מארצך וממולדתך ומבית אביך, Lech
lecha me'artzecha umimoladtecha umibeit avicha, right, ממולדתך ומבית אביך. Mimoladtecha umibeit avicha.
בית אב Beit Av means your tribe, your collective family. It doesn't
have to refer specifically to your actual father. And that is why
the daughters of כהנים should only marry כהנים so they never have
these issues. Okay, I think that this is the place that we're
going to stop. So, stop broadcast. Yeah, I know.